Guide to the Theater Three Collaborative Records, 1970-2014 RL.10145
David M. Rubenstein Rare Book & Manuscript Library
Theater Three Collaborative records
1970-2014
David M. Rubenstein Rare Book & Manuscript Library
Malpede, Karen
Human Rights Archive (Duke University)
Theater Three Collaborative
RL.10145
7 Linear Feet Five boxes; 18 GB of video
Theater Three Collaborative is a live theater production company creating plays about pressing social issues.
Historical note
Theater Three Collaborative is a live theater production company creating plays about pressing social issues. It was founded in 1995 by Lee Nagrin, George Bartenieff, and Karen Malpede and is based in Brooklyn, New York.
Provenance
The Theater Three Collaborative Records were received by the David M. Rubenstein Rare Book & Manuscript Library as a purchase in 2014.
Collection Overview
Collection consists largely of materials from plays written or directed by Theater Three Collaborative co-founder Karen Malpede, including The Beekeeper's Daughter, I Will Bear Witness, Prophecy, Iraq: Speaking of War, Another Life, and Extreme Whether. Each play addressed a social or human rights issue, such as Bosnian refugees, genetic engineering, torture and the Iraq War, global warming, and the Holocaust. Each play's materials usually include drafts and variations of scripts, production notes, publicity, photographs, and press reviews. A small amount of audiovisual material is included and is noted in the finding aid. Also includes some scripts and materials from George Bartenieff's roles in various productions, as well as some of Malpede's writings and essays, including her book The People's Theatre in Amerika.
Additional digital video files have been received but are not yet available for patron access. Contact Research Services with questions about accessing this collection's digital contents.
Access Restrictions
The majority of the collection is open for research. Digital files are unprocessed and are not available for patron use.
Researchers must register and agree to copyright and privacy laws before using this collection.
All or portions of this collection may be housed off-site in Duke University's Library Service Center. The library may require up to 48-hours to retrieve these materials for research use.
Please contact Research Services staff before visiting the David M. Rubenstein Rare Book & Manuscript Library to use this collection.
Experimental theater.; Women in the theater; Theater and society -- United States.; Bartenieff, George; Malpede, Karen; Human Rights Archive (Duke University); Theater Three Collaborative; Klemperer, Victor
- Theatrical Works, 1987-2013; 1
  - Us, 1987-2001; 1
    - Programs, reviews, and publicity, 1987-2001; 1 folders (Box 1)
  - Better People, 1990-1991; 2
    - Script, 1990; 1 folders (Box 1)
    - Script and notes, undated; 1 folders (Box 1)
    - Script, early draft, 1988; 1 folders (Box 6)
    - "Better People" in Angels of Power volume, 1991; 1 folders (Box 1)
      Scope and Contents note
      K. Malpede's work included in anthology edited by Susan Hawthorne and Renate Klein.
    - Excerpts for Issues in Reproductive and Genetic Engineering journal, 1991 (Box 1)
    - Promotional material, 1990 and undated; 1 folders (Box 6)
    - Reviews, rehearsal photographs, 1990; 1 folders (Box 1)
  - Going to Iraq, 1991-1992; 3
    - Clippings re: Gulf War, 1991; 1 folders (Box 1)
      Going to Iraq was also known as Blue Heaven.
    - "Peace Pieces" publication, 1991 June; 1 folders (Box 1)
      Includes K. Malpede's inserts.
    - Script, 1991 Sept. 23; 1 folders (Box 1)
    - Reviews, 1991; 1 folders (Box 1)
  - Collateral Damage, 1992; 4
    - Photographs, 1992; 1 folders (Box 1)
  - Kassandra, 1993; 5
    - Script, 1993; 1 folders (Box 1)
    - Photographs of rehearsals, 1993; 1 folders (Box 1)
    - NYU Production's tech week notes, etc., 1993; 1 folders (Box 1)
    - Publicity materials, 1993; 1 folders (Box 1)
    - Script working version, undated; 1 folders (Box 1)
  - The Beekeeper's Daughter, 1994-2013; 6
    - Dionysia World Festival, 1994; 1 folders (Box 1)
    - Italian script, 1994; 1 folders (Box 1)
    - Script with notes, 1994 Apr.-1995; 3 folders (Box 1)
      Folder 3 has additional notes re: Italy performance, 1994-1995.
    - Script, 1994 Apr.; 1 folders (Box 1)
    - Workshop production, 1995 Feb; 1 folders (Box 1)
    - Australian premiere, 1996; 1 folders (Box 1)
    - Script and production notes, 1997 Jan.; 1 folders (Box 1)
    - Script, revised, 1997 Jan.; 1 folders (Box 1)
    - Script and production notes, undated; 1 folders (Box 1)
    - Reviews, 1997; 1 folders (Box 1)
    - Rehearsal photographs, undated; 1 folders (Box 1)
    - Publicity, programs, undated; 1 folders (Box 1)
    - Promotional materials, 1995; 1 folders (Box 6)
    - Press clippings, 1995 and undated; 1 folders (Box 6)
    - Film right, correspondence with Other Pictures, 1996-1997; 1 folders (Box 1)
    - The Hum of the Bees film script, 2013 Apr. 30; 1 folders (Box 1)
    - "The Survivors' Eyes" essay by K. Malpede, undated; 1 folders (Box 1)
    - Budgets and financial statements, 1995-1997; 1 folders (Box 6)
    - Correspondence, generally regarding grants and donations, 1993-1996; 1 folders (Box 6)
  - I Will Bear Witness, 1998-2006; 7
    - Scripts for Parts 1 and 2, drafts, 2000; 1 folders (Box 2)
    - G. Bartenieff's rehearsal script, 2000; 1 folders (Box 2)
    - G. Bartenieff's script-in-progress, 2000; 2 folders (Box 2)
    - "Final" script, 2000 Mar.; 1 folders (Box 2)
    - Old script excerpt, undated; 1 folders (Box 6)
    - Script, 2000; 1 folders (Box 6)
    - K. Malpede's rehearsal script, 2000 Oct.; 1 folders (Box 2)
    - Script with lighting cues, 2000; 1 folders (Box 2)
    - Script of Part 1, 2000 Sept. 19; 1 folders (Box 2)
    - Rehearsal notes, diaries, script, etc., 2000-2001; 1 folders (Box 2)
    - Theater tech specifications, 2000-2001; 1 folders (Box 6)
      Scope and Contents
      Includes 2 photos of stage
    - Script with light plot cues, 2001; 1 folders (Box 2)
    - Miscellaneous notes, script excerpts, program drafts, 2001 and undated; 1 folders (Box 2)
    - Script, Part 1, 2003; 1 folders (Box 2)
    - G. Bartenieff's correspondence, notes, etc., 2001-2002; 1 folders (Box 2)
    - Correspondence between Bartenieff and Hadwig Klemperer, 2000s; 2 folders (Box 2)
    - General correspondence, 1997-2009; 6 folders (Box 6)
    - Staging and productions, 1998-2003; 1 folders (Box 2)
    - Publicity, staging, etc., 2002; 1 folders (Box 2)
    - Publicity, performances, press, 2000-2003; 1 folders (Box 2)
      Includes materials re: Bartenieff's OBIE.
    - London reviews, 2002 (Box 2)
    - Press clippings, 2000-2002; 1 folders (Box 6)
    - Promotional materials, 2001 and undated; 1 folders (Box 6)
    - Contracts and agreements, 1999-2002; 1 folders (Box 6)
    - G. Bartenieff's Jewish stars, research, undated; 1 folders (Box 2)
    - Interview transcripts with G. Bartenieff, 2006 Jun. 27; 1 folders (Box 2)
    - I Will Bear Witness, 1933-1941: A Diary of the Nazi Years, by Victor Klemperer, 1998; 1 Volumes (Box 2)
      K. Malpede's annotated copy.
    - To The Bitter End: The Diaries of Victor Klemperer 1942-1945, 1999; 1 Volumes (Box 2)
    - Mini-DVs of I Will Bear Witness, German tour, 2003; 15 items (Box 2)
    - Applications for grants and festivals, 1999-2001; 1 folders (Box 6)
    - Itinerary and monthly plans, February-April 2001; 1 folders (Box 6)
    - Handwritten notes, undated; 1 folders (Box 6)
    - Transcript of act II of performance, undated; 1 folders (Box 6)
    - Transcript of 2007 performance, 1 folders (Box 6)
    - Transcript of Berlin show, 19 September 2000; 1 folders (Box 6)
    - Transcript of Bartenieff interview, 27 June 2006; 1 folders (Box 6)
    - Transcipt of Bartenieff interview, undated; 1 folders (Box 6)
  - Iraq: Speaking of War, 2005-2006; 8
    - Permissions, correspondence, 2005-2006; 1 folders (Box 2)
    - Script, program draft, 2005; 1 folders (Box 2)
    - Publicity, programs, 2005; 1 folders (Box 2)
    - Script and program: Impact Festival, 2006 Sept. 28; 1 folders (Box 2)
    - Script: Culture Project version, 2006 Sept. 28; 1 folders (Box 2)
  - Prophecy, 2006-2010; 9
    - Correspondence, reactions, 2006-2010; 2 folders (Box 3)
    - Correspondence, general, 2008-2009; 1 folders (Box 6)
    - Programs, publicity, 2007-2008; 1 folders (Box 3)
      Includes DVD promo and dress rehearsal photo DVD (RL-10145-DVD-012).
    - Promotional materials, 2010 and undated; 1 folders (Box 6)
    - Press clippings, 2008-2010; 1 folders (Box 6)
    - Script with notes, 2008 Jun.; 2 folders (Box 3)
    - Script, 2007; 1 folders (Box 6)
    - Script, 2009 Jan.; 1 folders (Box 3)
    - Script with notes, 2009; 1 folders (Box 3)
    - Script and production notes, 2009; 1 folders (Box 3)
    - Production notes by K. Malpede, 2010; 1 folders (Box 3)
    - NYC production notes, diaries, correspondence, 2010 Mar.-Jun.; 1 folders (Box 3)
      Includes DVD of archival footage from Fourth St. Theater production.
    - Maxine's model figurines, undated; 1 folders (Box 3)
      2 small boxes of paper/foamboard figurines used in staging Prophecy.
    - TriQuarterly version, undated; 1 folders (Box 3)
      Issue no. 123 of TriQuarterly journal.
    - Festival of Conscience, 2012; 1 folders (Box 6)
    - Financial records, 2008-2009 and undated; 1 folders (Box 6)
    - Grant proposals, applications, and contracts, 2008-2009; 1 folders (Box 6)
  - Another Life, 2006-2014; 10
    - Articles and research, 2006-2010; 2 folders (Box 3)
    - K. Malpede's notebooks, undated; 1 folders (Box 3)
    - Malpede's production binder, March 2012; 2 folders (Box 6)
    - Early versions, notes, research, 2009-2012; 2 folders (Box 4)
      Folder 2 includes a DVD of archival footage from a reading with the cast in Sept. 2010, and photo DVDs from 2011 (RL-10145-DVD-013 and 014).
    - Another Life in The Kenyon Review, Fall 2010 (Box 4)
    - Articles on torture by K. Malpede, 2011-2014; 1 folders (Box 4)
    - Script rewrite, 2011 May 10; 1 folders (Box 4)
    - Script with edits, 2011 May 20; 1 folders (Box 4)
    - Script with edits, 2011 Jun. 4; 1 folders (Box 4)
    - Script with edits, 2011 Jun. 19; 1 folders (Box 4)
    - Script with notes, 2011 Aug.; 1 folders (Box 4)
    - Script, 2011 Oct.; 1 folders (Box 4)
    - Script with edits, 2011 Dec.; 1 folders (Box 4)
    - Script, 2011; 1 folders (Box 4)
    - G. Bartenieff's rehearsal script with cuts/restorations, 2011-2013; 1 folders (Box 4)
    - Scripts, 2012; 1 folders (Box 4)
    - Script, 2012 Mar.; 1 folders (Box 4)
    - "Final" script, 2013 Apr.; 1 folders (Box 4)
    - John Jay College's 9/11 Project, 2011-2014; 1 folders (Box 4)
      Promotional materials, etc. for Another Life and other performances. Includes DVD.
    - Production notes from tech week, 2013 Mar.; 1 folders (Box 4)
    - Project details and timelines, undated; 1 folders (Box 6)
    - Publicity, pamphlets, and programs, 2011-2013; 1 folders (Box 4)
      Includes DVD of production at Theater for the New City, 2013 Mar.-Apr.; DVD of production at Irondale Theater in Brooklyn, Mar. 2013; DVD of a reading with the cast at Dixon Place, Sept. 2010.
    - Promotional materials, undated; 1 folders (Box 6)
    - Another Life Playbook, published by Theater Three Collaborative, 2011 (Box 4)
    - RADA Festival, 2013 Jul.; 1 folders (Box 4)
    - Donation requests, undated; 1 folders (Box 6)
  - Extreme Whether, 2012-2013; 11
    - Script, 2012 Sept. 21; 1 folders (Box 4)
    - Script, undated; 1 folders (Box 6)
    - Script, 2012 Sept. 29; 1 folders (Box 4)
    - Script, 2013 Apr. 8 (Box 5)
    - Script, 2013 Apr. 12; 1 folders (Box 5)
    - Script, 2013 May 13; 1 folders (Box 5)
    - Script with notes, 2013 Jul. 9; 1 folders (Box 5)
    - Script, 2013 Aug. 28 (Box 5)
    - Script, undated; 1 folders (Box 5)
    - Publicity, 2013; 1 folders (Box 5)
      Includes promotional DVDs.
    - Promotional material, 2013-2014 and undated; 1 folders (Box 6)
    - Deed of gift, undated; 1 folders (Box 6)
  - The Painters Project, 2009
    - Artwork, 2009; 1 folders (Box 6)
    - Promotional materials, 2009; 1 folders (Box 6)
  - Angel's Elegy, 1994-1995
    - Budgets and financial statements, 1994-1995; 1 folders (Box 6)
- Administrative and Other Theater Materials, 1970-2012; 2
  - Karen Malpede's Materials
    - People's Theatre in Amerika clippings and research, 1970-1972 and undated; 1 folders (Box 5)
    - People's Theatre in Amerika correspondence with John Howard Lawson, 1970-1973 and undated; 1 folders (Box 5)
    - People's Theatre in Amerika correspondence re: writing and research, 1970-1972 and undated; 1 folders (Box 5)
      Includes book contract.
    - People's Theatre in Amerika published volume, 1972; 1 Volumes (Box 5)
    - Three Works by the Open Theater printed volume, 1974; 1 Volumes (Box 5)
    - A Monster Has Stolen the Sun and Other Plays printed volume, 1987; 1 Volumes (Box 5)
    - Typed diary and notes, 1988; 1 folders (Box 5)
      Unsorted loose pages.
    - "Cultural Diversity and Ideological Openness at the Cairo International Festival for Experimental Theater," New York Times article by Malpede, 1998; 1 folders (Box 5)
    - "Working with Dreams in Dubrovnik and Sarajevo," by Malpede in NTQ, 1996; 1 folders (Box 5)
    - "Idioms and Identities in Cairo," by Malpede in NTQ, 1998; 1 folders (Box 5)
    - Articles about K. Malpede, 1990s; 1 folders (Box 5)
    - Clippings of Malpede's early work, 1977-1979; 1 folders (Box 6)
    - Miscellaneous correspondence re: Malpede's stories, 2002-2012; 1 folders (Box 5)
    - Untitled notebooks, 1998-2008 and undated; 2 folders (Box 5)
    - Miscellaneous articles by K. Malpede, undated; 1 folders (Box 5)
    - Miscellaneous audiovisual materials, 1991-2004 and undated; 1 folders (Box 5)
      Includes 1 dvd titled "George L and O 'Evil Breeds'" (2004)
  - EcoFest, 1992-1994
    - Forms and applications, ca. 1993; 1 folders (Box 6)
    - Programs and schedules, 1993-1994; 1 folders (Box 6)
    - Correspondence, 1993; 1 folders (Box 6)
    - Promotional materials, 1992-1994; 1 folders (Box 6)
    - Miscellaneous notes, undated; 1 folders (Box 6)
  - George Bartenieff's Materials
    - Recommendation letters for George Bartenieff, 2005; 1 folders (Box 5)
    - George Bartenieff's correspondence, 1995-2010; 1 folders (Box 6)
    - Tuesdays with Morrie, 2002-2005; 1 folders (Box 6)
    - Interview with Clyde Fitch Report, 10 August 2012; 1 folders (Box 6)
  - Miscellaneous Materials
    - Clippings of Rosalie Sorrels, 1979-1992; 1 folders (Box 6)
    - Minutes of TTC Annual Board Meetings, 1996-1997; 1 folders (Box 6)
    - Clippings, 1989-2011 and undated; 1 folders (Box 6)
    - Theater Three Collaborative resumes, 1997-1998; 1 folders (Box 6)
- Audiovisual Materials
  Original audiovisual materials, including DVDs, miniDVs, and Betacams, featuring recordings of Theater Three Collaborative performances and rehearsals. Consult the AV inventory for more information.
  Access Restrictions
  Original audiovisual materials are closed to use. Contact Rubenstein in advance of your visit to request the production of access copies.
  - Audiovisual Materials (Box 7-8)